<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <string name="app_name">Eat Organic</string>

    <string-array name="planets_array">
        <item>	Artichokes	</item>
        <item>	Asian Greens  	</item>
        <item>	Asparagus  	</item>
        <item>	Beans  	</item>
        <item>	Beets  	</item>
        <item>	Blackberries  	</item>
        <item>	Blueberries  	</item>
        <item>	Broccoli  	</item>
        <item>	Brussels Sprouts	</item>
        <item>	Cabbage  	</item>
        <item>	Carrots  	</item>
        <item>	Cauliflower	</item>
        <item>	Celery  	</item>
        <item>	Cucumbers  	</item>
        <item>	Dry Beans and Peas	</item>
        <item>	Eggplant  	</item>
        <item>	Fennel	</item>
        <item>	Figs	</item>
        <item>	Fruit Trees	</item>
        <item>	Garlic	</item>
        <item>	Grapes	</item>
        <item>	Horseradish	</item>
        <item>	Jerusalem Artichokes	</item>
        <item>	Kale and Collards	</item>
        <item>	Kohlrabi	</item>
        <item>	Leeks	</item>
        <item>	Lettuce	</item>
        <item>	Melons	</item>
        <item>	Okra	</item>
        <item>	Onions	</item>
        <item>	Parsnips	</item>
        <item>	Peanuts	</item>
        <item>	Peas  	</item>
        <item>	Peppers	</item>
        <item>	Potatoes	</item>
        <item>	Pumpkins	</item>
        <item>	Radishes	</item>
        <item>	Raspberries	</item>
        <item>	Rhubarb	</item>
        <item>	Shallots	</item>
        <item>	Sorghum	</item>
        <item>	Sorrel	</item>
        <item>	Spinach  	</item>
        <item>	Stevia  	</item>
        <item>	Strawberries  	</item>
        <item>	Summer Grain Crops  	</item>
        <item>	Summer Squash	</item>
        <item>	Sweet Corn	</item>
        <item>	Sweet Potatoes	</item>
        <item>	Swiss Chard	</item>
        <item>	Tomatoes	</item>
        <item>	Turnips and Rutabagas	</item>
        <item>	Winter Grains	</item>
        <item>	Winter Squash  	</item>

    </string-array>


    <string-array name="plantation">
        <item>Start artichoke seeds indoors in late winter, under bright florescent lights. The large
            seeds will germinate within a week at warm room temperatures,and seedlings should be potted
            into larger containers as they grow. Six weeks before your last frost date, start hardening
            off seedlings by gradually exposing them to bright sun, wind and cool temperatures. \n\n
            Set artichoke plants out in prepared beds 3 to 4 weeks before your last frost date. Exposure to cool
            temperatures below 45 degrees is necessary to trigger flowering. Before transplanting artichokes,
            enrich each planting hole with a balanced organic fertilizer, and space plants 3 feet apart.
            Globe artichokes have average fertility needs, similar to those of tomatoes. In areas where artichokes are grown
            as perennials, container or bare-rooted plants can be set out in spring.  When setting out artichoke
            seedlings, plant them slightly high, so that the crown is well above the soil line.</item>


        <item>In late summer (six to 12 weeks before your  first fall frost), sow seeds indoors or
            direct-sow them in the garden if the weather is hot and dry. Transplant seedlings when
            they are four weeks old. Some Asian greens can also be grown in spring, but because spring
            crops are prone to bolting, be sure to choose bolt-resistant varieties, which will hold in
            the spring garden about 10 days longer than other varieties. All Asian greens grow best in moist,
            fertile, well-drained soil with a pH between 6.0 and 6.5. Choose a sunny site, loosen the soil to
            at least 12 inches deep, and thoroughly mix in a layer of mature compost. Sow seeds about 2 inches
            apart and a quarter inch deep, then water well to settle the seeds into the soil. After seeds germinate
            (often in less than five days), gradually thin them to proper spacing. Large Chinese cabbage,
            Chinese broccoli and flowering mustard should be thinned to 14 inches apart, but small
            bok choy plants do well with just 6 inches between plants.</item>



        <item>Plant asparagus crowns (dormant roots of  1-year-old plants) in spring at about the same
            time you would plant potatoes, but don’t rush to plant them if your soil is still cold. A few
            varieties, such as open-pollinated ‘Purple Passion’ and hybrid ‘Sweet Purple,’ can be grown
            from seed. Start seeds indoors in spring and set out the seedlings when they are 12 to 14
            weeks old, just after your last spring frost. Start with asparagus crowns, however, to
            eliminate the year of tedious weeding that comes with starting from seed. Choose a site
            with fertile soil that’s clear of perennial weeds and grasses. A single row of asparagus
            plants set 15 inches apart will fill in to form a 24- inch-wide bed, or you can grow a
            double row in a 36-inch-wide bed. Locate asparagus along the back or side of your garden,
            as 5-foot-tall asparagus fronds will shade any nearby plants. A bed of 25 mature plants
            will produce about 10 pounds of asparagus per year.\n\n
            Asparagus craves phosphorus, which is usually abundant in composted manure and in compost
            made from kitchen waste. Add a 2-inch layer of rich, weed-free compost to your soil before
            planting. Dig a trench 4 inches deep and 10 inches wide in the amended soil and arrange the
            crowns in the bottom, about 15 inches apart. Refill the trench without stepping on the bed.</item>


        <item>Bean seeds germinate best when soil  temperatures range between 60 and 70 degrees Fahrenheit.
            In spring, sow seeds in fertile, well-worked soil starting on or after your last frost date.
            When growing fast-maturing bush snap beans, make additional plantings at three-week intervals
            until midsummer. Prepare the planting bed by using a garden fork to loosen the soil. Mix in
            a 1-inch layer of mature compost. Plant seeds 1 inch deep and 2 to 4 inches apart. Thin bush beans
            to 4 inches apart; thin pole beans to 6 inches apart. Wide double rows (two parallel rows of beans
            planted 12 to 14 inches apart) are the most space-efficient way to grow beans.</item>


        <item>Begin planting beet seeds directly in the garden one month before your last spring frost date,
            followed by a second planting two to three weeks later. Beet seeds can germinate in cool soil,
            but they sprout best when soil temperatures are above 50 degrees Fahrenheit.
            Start planting beets for fall harvest 10 to 12 weeks before your expected first fall frost.
            Cultivate the planting site and mix in a 1-inch layer of cured compost and a standard application
            of organic fertilizer. As long as your soil is not alkaline, you can also mix in a sprinkling of
            wood ashes for additional potassium, which will support more vigorous beet growth. All beets grow
            best in fertile soil with a pH between 6.2 and 7.0. Water the prepared bed, and plant beet seeds
            half an inch deep and 2 inches apart, in rows spaced 12 inches apart.\n
            Beet seeds germinate in five to 10 days if kept constantly moist. Repeated watering can cause
            some soils to crust on the surface, which can inhibit the emergence of seedlings. Cover seeded
            rows with boards or burlap for a few days after planting to reduce surface crusting. This technique
            is also useful when planting beets for fall harvest in warm summer soil. Just be sure to remove the
            covers as soon as the beet seedlings break the surface.\n\n
            Beet seeds are actually capsules with two or more seeds inside, so thinning is essential to growing
            plump roots. Relieve early crowding by snipping out the weaker seedlings soon after germination.
            A week later, thin seedlings to 3 to 4 inches apart.\n</item>


        <item>Growing blackberries is easy in a sunny to partially shaded spot that has well-drained soil
            with a pH between 6.0 and 6.5. Enrich the site with plenty of organic matter so that the top 6
            inches of soil will retain moisture well. In garden-size plantings, allow 4 feet between erect
            and semi-trailing blackberry plants, or 6 to 8 feet between trailing varieties. Single plants
            of very productive varieties such as ‘Triple Crown’ can be grown on an upright pillar, or you
            can plant two or three plants together in a mound. Plant crowns about 3 inches deep, and water well.</item>


        <item>Late winter or early spring, during the six weeks prior to your last spring frost, is the best
            time for planting blueberries. Young container-grown plants may be set out later but need time
            to grow roots before hot weather. Blueberries are only marginally self-fertile, so you’ll need
            to grow at least three plants of compatible varieties. Choose a sunny, well-drained site that
            has an acidic pH for growing blueberry bushes. Young blueberry plants need an abundance of
            organic matter in the soil’s shallowest layers. Most soils should be amended with 4 inches
            of acidic organic matter, such as rotted sawdust or leaf compost. Preparing the site in fall
            will help the organic matter settle into the soil, which will enhance transplant survival in
            spring. If your soil’s natural pH ranges between 5.5 and 6.0, you can further acidify it by
            top-dressing with soil sulfur twice a year. In areas with soil pH levels above 6.0, grow
            blueberries in large containers filled with a wood chip- or bark-based planting mixture.\n\n

        Spacing recommendations for growing blueberries range from 12 inches between plants for lowbush
            blueberries to 12 feet between saskatoons. Allow 4 feet between highbush blueberry plants
            and 6 feet between rabbiteyes. Set plants at the same depth they grew in their pots. Water
            thoroughly, and mulch the soil’s surface with at least 2 inches of acidic mulch, such as
            wood chips. Cut back to ground level all but the two most vigorous upright shoots.\n</item>


        <item>For a summer harvest, start seeds indoors six weeks before your last spring frost, and
            set out hardened-off seedlings when they’re about four weeks old. You can also seed broccoli
            directly into a nursery bed and transplant the seedlings to your garden. Direct-sow broccoli
            raab starting three weeks before your last frost. For a fall harvest, start seeds indoors
            12 to 14 weeks before your first fall frost, and set the seedlings out when they’re four
            to six weeks old. Direct-sow broccoli raab starting eight weeks before your first fall frost.
            Broccoli is a heavy feeder, and plants take up nutrients best when the soil pH is between
            6.0 and 7.0. \n\nChoose a sunny site with fertile, well-drained soil. Loosen the planting bed
            and mix in up to 1 inch of mature compost. Unless your soil is very fertile, also mix in
            a high-nitrogen organic fertilizer such as alfalfa meal or composted poultry manure. Water
            the bed thoroughly before setting out seedlings. Allow 18 to 20 inches between plants.
            Dwarf varieties can be planted 12 inches apart.\n</item>


        \n<item>Unlike cabbage and broccoli, growing Brussels sprouts is seldom successful from plants
            set out in spring. Hot weather that arrives just as spring-planted sprouts start sprouting
            ruins their flavor and texture, and the plants become magnets for insects.
            It is much better to wait until late spring or early summer to start Brussels sprout seeds.
            Recommended seeding dates for a few locations include March 30 in Rhode Island, May 15 in
            New York, June 5 in West Virginia, and July 1 in Alabama. Harden off the seedlings before
            setting them out in well-prepared soil, and plan to cover them with lightweight row cover
            or tulle to exclude insect pests.\n\n
            Brussels sprouts are heavy feeders that demand moist, fertile soil with a pH between 6.0 and 7.0.
            The ideal soil texture for Brussels sprouts is clay, because tight clay helps hold the roots firm
            when the large plants are blown by harsh winds. Mix in a generous application of a balanced organic
            fertilizer before planting, and use a biodegradable mulch of grass clippings or coarse compost to
            insulate the roots from summer’s heat.\n</item>


        <item>In spring, start seeds indoors or in a cold frame eight to 10 weeks before your last spring frost,
            and set out hardened-off seedlings when they are about 6 weeks old. Seeds germinate best
            at 65 to 75 degrees Fahrenheit.\n\n
            In summer, start seeds 12 to 14 weeks before your first fall frost, and transplant the
            seedlings to the garden when they are 4 to 6 weeks old. Plant early and late varieties to
            stretch your harvest season. Growing cabbage plants requires regular feeding and abundant sun.
            Choose a sunny, well-drained site with fertile soil that has a pH between 6.0 and 6.5.\n\n
            Loosen the planting bed and mix in a 2-inch layer of compost along with a standard application
            of a balanced organic fertilizer or well-composted manure. Water the fertilized bed thoroughly
            before setting out seedlings. Allow 18 to 20 inches between plants for 4-pound varieties; larger
            varieties may need more room. Varieties that will produce heads that weigh less than 2 pounds
            (check your seed packet) can be spaced 12 inches apart.</item>


        <item>In the spring, sow carrot seeds in fertile, well-worked soil about two weeks before your last frost date.
            In cool climates, continue planting every three weeks until midsummer. In summer, begin sowing seeds for
            fall and winter carrots 10 to 12 weeks before your average first fall frost.</item>


        <item>Unlike cabbage and broccoli, cauliflower can rarely be grown successfully from plants set out
            in spring. Hot weather that arrives just as spring-planted cauliflower heads up ruins its flavor
            and texture, and the plants become magnets for insects. A much better planting schedule is to wait
            until late spring or early summer to start cauliflower seeds.\n \n Harden off the seedlings before setting them out
            in well-prepared soil, and plan to cover them with lightweight row cover or tulle to exclude insect pests.
            Cauliflower plants are heavy feeders that demand moist, fertile soil with a pH between 6.0 and 7.0.
            Mix in a generous application of a balanced organic fertilizer before planting, and allow at least
            24 inches between plants (because tight spacing will lead to small heads). Use a biodegradable mulch
            of grass clippings or coarse compost to insulate the roots from summer heat.</item>


        <item>Celery seeds of all types are small and may germinate erratically. Start them in doors
            or in a greenhouse 10 to 12 weeks before your last spring frost and give them bright light.
            Seedlings that have more than five leaves can be hardened off and set out when average night
            temperatures are above 55 degrees Fahrenheit. Exposure to cold for more than a week can trigger
            plants to bolt and produce seeds. In hot summer areas with mild winters, start seeds indoors in
            late summer and set them out in early fall.\n \n Plants should be ready to harvest about 90 days
            after you put your seedlings in the ground.Choose a sunny site that is convenient to water,
            because celery requires constant moisture. If possible, allow space between rows for a shallow
            trench that can be flooded with water in dry weather. Dig in a 1-inch layer of rich compost and
            a standard application of a high-nitrogen organic fertilizer, such as dried poultry manure,
            and water well. Wait at least three days before planting seedlings 12 to 14 inches apart.
            Before hot weather comes, mulch between plants with grass clippings or another organic mulch
            to keep the soil cool and moist.</item>


        <item>Sow seeds directly into prepared rows or hills one to two weeks after your last
            spring frost, and make a second planting a month later. Where summers are short and cool,
            start seeds indoors under bright fluorescent lights two weeks before your last spring frost.
            If kept moist and warm (above 70 degrees Fahrenheit), cucum­ber seeds should sprout within
            five days. Set out 3- to 4-week-old seedlings after your last frost has passed. Choose a
            sunny site with fertile, well-drained soil with a pH between 6.0 and 6.5. Grow cucumbers in rows
            or hills spaced 6 feet apart, or try increasing yields by training vines up a vertical trellis.

            \n\nMix a 2-inch layer of rich compost into the planting site, along with a light application
            of an organic fertilizer. Thoroughly water the soil before plant­ing seeds half an inch deep
            and 6 inches apart. When the seedlings have three leaves, thin them to 12 inches apart, which
            is the spacing you should use if transplanting seedlings.</item>


        <item>In early spring, sow soup peas in fertile beds four to six weeks before your last frost.
            All other dry beans and peas are warm-weather crops best sown in late spring and summer.
            Sow these seeds in fertile soil starting no earlier than two weeks after your last frost date.
            In areas with long summers, later plantings made in June may have the advantage of ripening
            during the typically dry weather of early fall, when scant rain reduces chances that pods will rot.
            In any climate, traditional dry beans with a bush habit can be planted up to 90 days before
            your first fall frost date.</item>


        <item>Start eggplant seeds indoors about six weeks before your last spring frost, or about two
            weeks after tomatoes and peppers. Eggplant seeds germinate best at temperatures above 75 degrees
            Fahrenheit. Bottom heat is useful in getting the plants up and growing. Keep these members of
            the nightshade family growing under bright fluorescent lights for 14 to 16 hours each day,
            and transplant them to 4-inch containers when they have three leaves. Move plants outdoors on warm,
            sunny days, but bring them indoors when temperatures drop below 55 degrees. Set out hardened-off
            seedlings when they are about eight weeks old. When planning your garden, allow one plant per person,
            as a healthy plant will produce about 5 pounds of eggplant over two months or more. Choose a sunny,
            well-drained site with fertile soil (pH between 5.5 and 6.5). \n\n To reduce pest problems, choose a spot
            where nightshade family members (eggplants, tomatoes, potatoes or peppers) have not been grown
            for at least two years. Two weeks before planting, loosen the planting bed and mix in a 2-inch layer
            of rich compost along with a standard application of balanced organic fertilizer or composted
            poultry manure and water well. In cool climates, cover the prepared bed with black plastic film
            to help warm the soil. Allow 24 inches between plants and plan ahead for stakes or other supports.
            In most regions you’ll need to cover newly transplanted eggplants with row covers to exclude flea
            beetles and other pests. Once plants are about 14 inches tall they are tough enough to fend for
            themselves and at this height you can remove covers to admit pollinators.</item>


        <item>Start bulb fennel seeds indoors in early spring, about 8 weeks before your last frost, and set
            them out under cloches when they have one true leaf. When growing fennel, prepare a fertile,
            well-drained bed in a spot that is convenient to water, because bulb fennel must have moist soil.
            Mix a standard application of a balanced organic fertilizer into the soil before setting out plants.
            Fennel seeds also may be sown directly where they are to grow about three weeks before your last spring frost
            date. Space plants at least 12 inches apart. Start seeds for a fall planting of bulb fennel in midsummer,
            and set them out about 8 weeks before your first fall frost date. When growing fennel in fall, harvest
            bulbs before they are damaged by hard freezes.\n\n
            Herb fennel is grown just like bulb fennel, but only one or two plants are needed by most households.
            Perennial fennel plants that are grown to produce fennel fronds and fennel seeds grow quite tall, to 5 feet,
            so they often are best located near the rear of the garden.</item>

        \n<item>Set out figs in spring, after risk of a hard freeze has passed. Figs grow best in fertile, well-drained
            soil with a pH between 6.0 and 6.5. Enrich the site with plenty of organic matter so that the top 12 inches
            of soil will retain moisture well. Allow at least 6 feet between plants, or 15 feet between them in climates
            where figs grow into trees.\n\n
            In most climates, figs are most productive when trained to grow as multi-stemmed bushes. Top back the plant
            by half its size after transplanting to encourage the development of new stems. Mulch figs to suppress weeds
            and keep the soil moist.</item>

        <item>The best time to plant fruit trees in Zones 3 through 7 is early spring, after the soil has thawed.
            Fruit trees that are set out just as they emerge from winter dormancy will rapidly grow new roots.
            In Zones 8 to 10, plant new trees in February. Choose a sunny site with fertile, well-drained soil
            that’s not in a low frost pocket. Dig a planting hole that’s twice the size of the root ball of the tree.
            Carefully spread the roots in the hole, and backfill with soil. Set trees at the same depth at which they
            grew at the nursery, taking care not to bury any graft union (swollen area) that’s on the main trunk.
            Water well, and install a trunk guard made of hardware cloth or spiral plastic over the lowest section
            of the trunk to protect it from insects, rodents, sunscald and physical injuries. Stake the tree loosely
            to hold it steady. Mulch over the root zone of the planted trees with wood chips, sawdust or another
            slow-rotting mulch. Water particularly well during any dry spells for the first two years.\n\n
            One year after planting, fertilize fruit trees in spring by raking back the mulch and scratching a balanced
            organic fertilizer into the soil surface (follow application rates on the product’s label).
            Then add a wood-based mulch to bring the mulch depth up to 4 inches in a 4-foot circle around the tree.
            After two years, stop using trunk guards and instead switch to coating the trunks with white latex
            paint to defend against winter injuries. Add sand to the paint to deter rabbits and voles.</item>


        <item>In fall, plant cloves in well-drained beds after the first frost has passed and the soil is cool.
            Cloves can also be planted in late winter as soon as the soil thaws, but fall-planted garlic
            produces bigger, better bulbs. Choose a sunny site, and loosen the planting bed to at least 12 inches deep.
            Thoroughly mix in a 1-inch layer of mature compost. \n\nIn acidic soil, also mix in a light dusting of wood ashes.
            Wait until just before planting to break bulbs into cloves. Poke the cloves into the ground 4 inches
            deep and 6 to 8 inches apart, with their pointed ends up. Cover the planted area with 3 to 5 inches of organic mulch,
            such as hay or shredded leaves.</item>


        <item>In spring, set out purchased plants four to six weeks before your last frost, when the plants are
            emerging from dormancy. Grape varieties grown in containers can be planted up until early summer.
            Growing grapes in full sun helps develop sweet, full-flavored fruits. Plants can produce fruit for
            decades if grown in deep, fertile soil that drains well. Before planting, dig out all perennial
            weeds and amend the soil with at least 2 inches of mature compost or other high-quality organic matter.
            If your soil tends to be acidic, use light applications of lime or wood ashes to raise the pH levels
            to between 5.6 and 6.2.\n\n

            Most grapes should be planted 7 to 9 feet apart, with a durable trellis installed at planting time.
            After planting grapes, water them thoroughly and mulch the area beneath the plants with 2 to 4
            inches of wood chips or another organic mulch.</item>

        <item>Planting horseradish is best done is spring, whether you begin with crowns from a nursery,
            or a root from the supermarket. Most households harvest enough horseradish for their needs from
            two or three plants. Set out roots or crowns a few weeks before your last frost date, in any fertile,
            well-drained soil. Horseradish grows best in moist, silty soils like those found in river bottomland,
            but enriched clay or sandy loam with a near neutral pH is acceptable. Situate horseradish roots diagonally
            in the soil, with the slanted end down and the flat end up. </item>


        <item>Plant small, whole tubers in early spring, or as late as you’d plant tomatoes. To get Jerusalem
            artichokes with big roots, give plants the longest growing season possible. After the first year,
            small tubers you missed while harvesting will usually shoot up sufficient plants to form a good crop.
            A hardy, widely adapted perennial, Jerusalem artichokes grow best in well-drained soil with a near-neutral
            pH of about 7.0. Locate your crop in full sun but behind smaller vegetables, because the 10-foot-tall
            plants cast ample afternoon shade. A 5-by-5-foot bed (located outside the garden, where its perimeter
            can be easily mowed) is ideal for this exuberant crop. A 25-square-foot planting can produce more than
            100 pounds of harvested tubers.\n\n
            To prepare the site, dig out weeds and grasses, and dig in a 2-inch layer of compost to improve the
            soil’s structure. Plant small seed tubers 4 to 5 inches deep and 16 inches apart. When the plants are
            about a foot tall, mulch with grass clippings, rotting leaves, or another organic mulch that will help
            retain soil moisture.</item>


        <item>You can grow kale or collards from seeds sown directly into prepared soil, but especially in
            spring it’s best to start seeds indoors and set them out under protective cloches four to six weeks
            before your last spring frost. As long as they are protected from cold winds, kale or collards
            transplanted into cool soil will quickly establish themselves and start growing.
            Kale and collard greens grown in spring often become magnets for pests in early summer, so most gardeners
            pull up the plants and compost them. Then, in July or August, new seedlings are started that
            will serve as the fall to winter crop.\n\n
            Recommended seeding dates for growing kale and collards in fall include late June in New Hampshire,
            early July in Maryland, late July in Alabama, and late August in Arizona. Harden off the seedlings
            before setting them out in well-prepared soil, and plan to cover them with lightweight row cover or
            tulle to exclude insect pests and provide a little bit of shade. Kale and collard plants are heavy
            feeders that grow best in moist, fertile soil with a pH between 6.0 and 7.5. Mix in a generous
            application of a balanced organic fertilizer before planting, and allow at least 12 inches between plants.
            Use a biodegradable mulch of grass clippings or coarse compost to insulate the roots from any warm weather.</item>

        <item>For your first spring sowing of kohlrabi, start seeds indoors about six weeks before your last
            spring frost date. Kohlrabi is not as cold-tolerant as other cabbage family crops, so wait until
            two weeks before your last frost date to set out seedlings. This is also the best time to direct-sow
            seeds in a well-prepared bed.\n\n
            Kohlrabi plants are heavy feeders that demand moist, fertile soil with a pH between 6.0 and 7.5.
            Micronutrients are important, so take the time to amend the soil with compost and a standard application
            of a balanced organic fertilizer before planting. Thin or transplant seedlings to 8 inches apart, but
            allow more space when growing large, vigorous storage varieties. When growing kohlrabi in spring, use
            a biodegradable mulch of grass clippings or coarse compost to insulate the roots from summer’s heat.\n\n
            Start seeds of storage varieties in midsummer, at about the same time you would sow broccoli or cabbage
            for fall harvest. This is usually about 90 days before your average first fall frost date. Harden off the
            seedlings before setting them out in well-prepared soil, and plan to cover them with lightweight row cover
            or tulle to exclude insect pests.</item>

        <item>Start leek seeds indoors in late winter provided you can grow them under bright florescent lights.
            You may also be able to purchase leek seedlings as garden centers or farmers markets in late spring.
            Harden off seedlings for at least a week before transplanting them to prepared furrows in deeply dug
            garden beds. Shape 6-inch deep furrows in the cultivated bed, and line the bottom with a standard
            application of a balanced organic fertilizer. Refill 1 inch of soil, and set out the leek seedlings
            in the partially refilled furrow, spacing summer leeks 3 inches apart, fall leeks 4 inches apart and
            winter leeks 6 inches apart. As the leeks gain size, gradually fill in the furrow and then mound a
            little loose soil over the base of the plants.</item>


        <item>In spring, sow lettuce in cold frames or tunnels six weeks before your last frost date.
            Start more seeds indoors under lights at about the same time, and set them out when they are
            three weeks old. Direct seed more lettuce two weeks before your average last spring frost date.
            Lettuce seeds typically sprout in two to eight days when soil temperatures range between 55 and 75 degrees.

            \n\nIn fall, sow all types of lettuce at two-week intervals starting eight weeks before your first fall frost.
            One month before your first frost, sow only cold-tolerant butterheads and romaines. Prepare your
            planting bed by loosening the soil to at least 10 inches deep. Mix in an inch or so of good compost
            or well-rotted manure. Sow lettuce seeds a quarter of an inch deep and 1 inch apart in rows or squares,
            or simply broadcast them over the bed.\n\n

            Indoors, sow lettuce seeds in flats or small containers kept under fluorescent lights.
            Harden off three-week-old seedlings for at least two or three days before transplanting.
            Use shade covers, such as pails or flowerpots, to protect transplants from sun and wind
            during their first few days in the garden. </item>


        <item>Sow muskmelons, honeydew and other Cucumis melo varieties in prepared beds or hills after
            your last frost has passed, or sow seeds indoors under fluorescent light and set the seedlings
            out after about three weeks. Direct sow watermelon seeds in late spring or early summer,
            when your soil feels warm to the touch. In short-season climates, plant watermelon seedlings
            started indoors to get a jump-start on the growing season.Fertile, well-drained soil is essential to
            growing great melons. Prepare raised planting hills within wide rows or along your garden’s edge.
            Space 3-foot-wide hills 5 to 6 feet apart. Loosen the soil in the planting sites to at least 12
            inches deep. Mix in a 2-inch layer of compost and a light application of organic fertilizer.
            \n\nMelons love composted manure (from cows, horses or poultry), which eliminates the need for
            supplemental fertilizer. Use a rake to shape the hills into 6- to 8-inch-high, flat-topped
            mounds, and water well. Plant six seeds per hill, poking them into the soil 1 inch deep.
            en days after sowing, thin plants to three per hill. If planting seedlings, set out three
            seedlings for each hill.\n\n
            Consider installing protective row covers after you finish planting melons. Row covers benefit
            melons by raising soil surface temperatures, taming wind and excluding insects. Remove covers
            a week after plants begin to bloom so insects can pollinate the flowers</item>

        <item>Okra will grow in a range of soil types provided the pH is between 5.8 and 6.8. Maximize
            sun exposure when growing okra, because this crop cannot tolerate shade. Loosen the soil to
            at least 12 inches, and mix in a 1 inch layer of compost along with a standard application
            of a balanced organic fertilizer. \n\nPlant okra in late spring or early summer, two weeks or
            more after your last frost has passed. Soak hard okra seeds in plain water overnight before
            planting, and discard any seeds that float to the top. Plant okra seeds 1 inch deep and 4
            inches apart, spacing rows at least 30 inches apart. When okra seedlings are 4 inches tall,
            thin them to at least 18 inches apart.\n\n
            Dwarf okra varieties can be grown in containers that are at least 12 inches in diameter.
            Three plants will fit into a planter made out of a modified plastic storage bin.</item>

        <item>In late winter, start seeds of all types of onions — bulb onions, leeks, scallions,
            and shallots — indoors under bright fluorescent lights. Make additional sowings until
            early spring. Set out bulb onion seedlings three weeks before your last frost, and set
            out seedlings of non-bulbing onions six weeks before your last frost.\n\n
            In spring you can also plant sets, which are small, dormant onions. Small sets produce better bulbs
            than large sets do.In fall, short-day varieties can be planted in many mild winter areas.
            Seedlings should be ready to set out in mid-October. Choose a sunny site with fertile,
            well-drained soil, and loosen the planting bed to at least 12 inches deep. Mix in a 1-inch
            layer of mature compost. Make a 4-inch-deep, V-shaped furrow in the prepared bed. Fill the
            bottom of the furrow with 1 inch of rich compost or a light dusting of dry organic fertilizer,
            and then water the prepared furrow. Set out seedlings or sets 3 to 6 inches apart, depending
            on the plants’ mature size.</item>


        <item>Parsnip seeds quickly lose viability after their first year, so buy fresh seed or grow
            your own seed crop at least every other year. Where summers are short and mild, plant parsnips
            in late spring, a week or two after the last frost has passed. In other areas it is often best
            to delay planting until early summer, or about four months before your first fall frost date.
            One week before planting parsnips, place parsnip seeds on a wet paper towel and enclose it
            in an airtight container. After five days at room temperature, look for the emergence of pale
            white sprouts. When the first seeds begin to germinate, plant all of the seeds one-half inch
            deep and two inches apart in well-prepared beds that have been generously enriched with compost
            and a standard application of a balanced organic fertilizer. Keep the planting weeded well, and
            gradually thin parsnips to at least 6 inches apart.</item>


        <item>Peanuts grow best in slightly acidic, sandy soil with a pH between 5.8 and 6.2. Plant peanuts
            at least two weeks after the last frost has passed, when the soil is warm. Wait until just before
            planting to remove the seeds from the shells. Rather than applying pre-plant fertilizer, it is best
            to plant peanuts after a heavily fertilized non-legume crop such as corn or cabbage.
            Sow peanut seeds 2 inches deep and 6 to 8 inches apart, with at least 24 inches between rows.
            Thin seedlings to 12 inches apart. Peanuts also can be grown in hills, with three plants per
            3-foot-wide hill. You can interplant peanuts with spring radishes or lettuce to suppress weeds.</item>

        <item>Sow in spring, about one month before your last frost date. Where summers are cool,
            additional sowings can be made three weeks apart. Peas produce poorly in hot weather, so an early start
            is always a wise strategy. In climates with mild winters, a second crop can be sown in late summer for
            harvesting in late fall.All peas benefit from a trellis or other support. Install a 6-foot-tall trellis
            before planting long-vined varieties. Compact varieties can be staked with woody branches or unemployed
            tomato cages after they sprout, or you can interplant short-vined peas with oats, which serve as a living support.

            \n\nPrepare a wide planting bed by loosening the soil to at least 10 inches deep while mixing in compost.
            Do not use fertilizer unless your soil is very poor or low in organic matter. Plant seeds in a double
            row, with a row of seeds on each side of the trellis. Poke seeds into the prepared site 2 inches apart
            and 1 inch deep. Thinning is not necessary.</item>


        <item>Start seeds indoors under bright fluorescent  lights in early spring, eight to 10 weeks before your
            last spring frost date. If possible, provide bottom heat to keep the plants’ containers near 80 degrees
            Fahrenheit. Make sure the seeds stay slightly moist. Seeds should sprout within three weeks. Transfer
            seedlings to larger containers when they are about six weeks old. Don’t set peppers outside until at
            least two weeks after your average last frost date, during a period of warm weather. (To find your last
            spring frost date, see Know When to Plant What: Find Your Average Last Spring Frost Date.) Always harden
            off seedlings by gradually exposing them to outdoor weather a few hours each day for at least a week before
            transplanting them outdoors. \n\nAll peppers grow best under warm conditions, but gardeners in cool climates
            can keep peppers happy by using row covers. Choose a sunny site that has fertile, well-drained soil with
            a pH between 6.0 and 6.5. Loosen the planting bed to 12 inches deep, and thoroughly mix in a 1-inch layer
            of mature compost. Dig planting holes 12 inches deep and at least 18 inches apart, and enrich each with a
            spadeful of additional compost. Partially refill the holes, and situate plants so they are planted slightly
            deeper than they were in their containers. Water well.</item>

        <item>In climates with short springs and hot summers, plant the early and midseason varieties three to
            four weeks before your last spring frost date. In climates with long springs and hot summers,
            plant early and midseason varieties three to four weeks before your last spring frost date;
            plant late-maturing varieties in early summer so they will mature in the cooler fall.\n\n
            In climates with cool summers, plant early, midseason and late varieties two to three weeks
            before your last spring frost date. Prepare the planting bed by loosening the soil to at least
            10 inches deep. Potatoes adapt well to acidic soils with a pH below 6.0, which is lower than what
            is preferred by many other vegetable crops. Thoroughly mix in a layer of compost or rotted leaves,
            along with a half-ration of alfalfa meal, soybean meal or another high-nitrogen organic fertilizer
            (follow label directions). Do not use manure because it is correlated with an increase in rough
            patches on spud skins.\n\n
            Two days before planting, cut the seed potatoes into pieces, so that each piece has two to
            three buds (or “eyes”). Cutting the seed potatoes and letting the cut pieces dry for about
            two days reduces the risk of rotting. Work carefully if the eyes have already grown into sprouts.
            Allow the cut pieces to dry in a well-ventilated room. Plant the pieces 12 inches apart in 4-inch
            deep furrows; cover the seed pieces with 2 inches of soil. Fill in the furrows after the first
            sprouts emerge.</item>

        <item>Sow pumpkin seeds directly into prepared beds or hills in late spring, after your last frost.
            Or, try what many gardeners in cool climates do, and set out 3-week-old seedlings in late spring.
            In Zone 6 and warmer, delay planting pumpkins until early summer to use space vacated by spring crops,
            and use container-grown seedlings to get summer-planted pumpkins growing on time.\n\n

            Stop planting pumpkins 14 weeks before your first fall frost. Choose a sunny site with fertile,
            well-drained soil and a pH level between 5.8 and 6.8. Moschata pumpkins need little pest protection,
            so many gardeners grow them in an old compost pile that includes composted manure. Other types of
            pumpkins benefit from the pest protection of floating row covers for at least six weeks after planting,
            in which case it is most practical to start them in a row, spacing plants 3 feet apart
            (large-fruited pumpkin varieties may need more room). As you prepare planting holes, mix in a 2-inch
            layer of mature compost and a light application of a balanced organic fertilizer. Water well.
            Plant two seeds (or one seedling) in each prepared hole. Install protective row covers over your
            pumpkins immediately after you plant them. Expect pumpkin vines to run at least 8 feet.</item>

        <item>In spring, sow salad radishes at 10-day intervals starting two weeks before your average
            last spring frost, continuing to three weeks after your last frost date. Sow rat-tail radishes
            around your last spring frost date.\n\n
            In fall, sow all types of radishes at two-week intervals starting eight weeks before your
            first fall frost, continuing up until three weeks before your first frost date.When preparing
            the planting bed, loosen the soil 6 to 10 inches deep, and mix in good compost or well-rotted manure.
            Sow seeds a half inch deep and 1 inch apart, in rows spaced 12 inches apart. After the seedlings appear,
            thin salad radishes to 3 inches apart; thin oriental radishes to 8 to 10 inches apart. Seeds typically
            sprout in three to seven days when sown in 60-degree soil.</item>

        <item>In spring, set out dormant, bare-root plants four to six weeks before your last frost.
            Raspberry plants grown in containers should be planted after danger of frost has passed
            through early summer. Set plants 1 inch deeper than they grew in their nursery containers.
            Raspberries need some afternoon shade if grown in hot climates, but in most regions, full
            sun is key to growing raspberries with rich, sweet flavor. Raspberries can produce for many
            years if grown in fertile, weed-free soil that drains well and has a pH of about 6.0. Before
            planting, dig out all perennial weeds and amend the soil with at least 2 inches of mature
            compost or other high-quality organic matter. Use a digging fork to loosen dense subsoil to
            improve drainage.\n\n
            If your soil is acidic, use light applications of lime or wood ash to raise the pH.
            (Take care, though, as a pH above 7.0 can render raspberries unable to take up iron and manganese.)
            Red and golden raspberries have a bushy growth habit and grow well on a garden fence or trellis.
            Black and purple raspberries need more space and are best grown as a thicket with a mowed
            perimeter.</item>

        <item>Instead of seeds you should buy rhubarb plants, which won’t cost much because you need
            only a few. As a general rule, allow only one plant per person in your household unless
            you have space to spare for these big plants, which mature to 4 to 5 feet across.
            Planting rhubarb is best done in spring, around your last frost date. Plant in moist,
            fertile soil in full sun to partial afternoon shade, but note that rhubarb plants can
            be moved at other times of the year if soil is kept packed around their roots. Space plants
            4 to 5 feet apart, or use them as a focal points dotted around your garden’s boundary.
            Enrich planting holes generously with compost as well as a standard application of a balanced
            organic fertilizer when planting rhubarb.</item>


        <item>Fall planting works well when growing shallots from cloves that are showing signs of
            breaking dormancy, or you can wait until first thing in spring. Fall planting is recommended
            with gray shallots, which often break dormancy in fall.\n\n
            Red and gold shallots, particularly those grown from seed, are in a state of deep dormancy
            in the fall, so it is usually best to wait until early spring to plant them. Seed-sown shallots
            grown as annuals should be started indoors under lights in late winter, so that sturdy seedlings
            are ready to set out four to six weeks before your last frost. Though they start out growing slowly,
            shallot seedlings are sturdy, fast-growing plants compared with bulb onion seedlings.
            \n\nHarden off shallot seedlings for at least a week before transplanting them to prepared furrows
            in deeply dug garden beds. Shape 6-inch-deep furrows in a cultivated bed, and line the bottom
            with a standard application of a balanced organic fertilizer. Refill 3 inches of soil, and set
            out the seedlings 8 inches apart in all directions. </item>


        <item>There is no rush to plant sorghum, which needs warm soil to germinate and grow. Even in warm
            climates, sorghum is customarily planted in late May or early June.\n\n
            Prepare soil much as you would for corn, and be sure to mix a balanced organic fertilizer into
            the bed or row before planting. Unlike corn, sorghum is self-fertile, so a large plot is not
            needed for pollination purposes. Sow seeds one-half inch deep and 4 inches apart, and thin to
            8 inches apart when the seedlings are 4 inches tall.</item>


        <item>Sorrel can be grown from seeds started indoors in early spring, or you can purchase a plant
            from a nursery. After established, one or two plants will grow into a patch that will produce
            enough sorrel for most households. Set out plants in spring, around your last frost date,
            in any fertile, well drained soil. Sorrel plants tolerate light frosts.</item>


        <item>In late winter, beginning six weeks before your average last spring frost date, start seeds
            indoors or beneath a protective frame outdoors. Make two additional spring sowings at three-week
            intervals.\n\n
            In summer, skip spinach and try the warm-weather alternatives. In fall, six to seven weeks before your first
            fall frost date, sow your main crop for fall harvest.\n\n
            About four weeks before your first fall frost date, sow winter spinach in a place where the seedlings
            can be covered in frigid weather with glass, plastic or a thick row cover. This planting will mature
            in early spring.</item>

        <item></item>

        \n<item>Growing strawberries requires sun and  acidic soil with a pH between 5.5 and 6.5. Plant
            strawberries as early as six weeks before your last frost. Use row covers to protect new
            plantings from extreme cold and wind. You can also set out plants in fall, which is a common
            practice where winters are mild. Choose a sunny, fertile site free of perennial weeds.
            A strawberry patch will produce well for three to four years, so enrich the site with plenty
            of organic matter. Raised beds or planters are ideal for most types of strawberries,
            plus they make the berries easier to pick.\n\n
            A few varieties can be grown from seed, but most gardeners save one to two years’ growing
            time by setting out individual container-grown plants or dormant bare-root plants sold in bunches.
            Transplant individual plants to the same depth they grew in their containers. Spread out bundled
            plants and trim off any dead leaves and roots. Find the central crown, and transplant so the base
            of the crown rests at the soil line and the roots are spread out. Mulch between all strawberry
            plants with pine needles, chopped leaves or another mulch that supports acidic soil conditions.

            \n\nSpace requirements vary by strawberry type and variety. Those that produce a lot of vigorous
            runners should be planted 18 inches apart (they will fill in most of the vacant space by late summer).
            Plant alpine strawberries that do not produce runners — such as ‘Mignonette’ — 12 inches apart
            in beds or 8 inches apart in containers.</item>


        <item>Growing buckwheat and oats is an excellent practice if your soil is in the early stages of
            organic improvement, because these crops will grow fast and smother weeds if grown in broad swaths.
            Start sowing seeds of these summer grain crops in late spring, after your last frost has passed
            and the soil has warmed. Cultivate the soil to remove weeds and rocks, and mix in a standard
            application of a balanced organic fertilizer before planting buckwheat or hulless oat seeds a
            bout 2 inches apart. When the plants are 4 inches tall, hoe to remove weeds, and thin the
            plants to 6 inches apart.\n\n
            Corn, pearl millet and sunflowers grow into large plants that benefit from fertile, well-drained soil.
            Grow these summer grain crops much as you would sweet corn. Enrich planting furrows with an organic
            fertilizer, and space rows at least 18 inches apart. Thin corn and sunflower plants to at
            least 14 inches apart. Grow pearl millet at a tighter spacing, about 10 inches apart.</item>

        <item>Sow summer squash seeds in prepared  beds or hills in spring after all danger of frost has passed.
            You can also sow seeds indoors under fluorescent lights and then set out the seedlings when they’re
            3 weeks old. In Zone 5 and warmer, you can sidestep early-season squash bugs by delaying the planting
            of seedlings until early summer. Stop planting summer squash 12 weeks before your average first fall
            frost date. Choose a sunny site with fertile, well-drained soil with a pH between 6.0 and 6.5 for
            growing summer squash. Spots that were previously occupied by compost piles are especially desirable,
            or you can dig two heaping spadefuls of compost into each planting site. As you dig, loosen the soil
            to at least 12 inches deep and mix in a light application of a balanced organic fertilizer.\n\n

            Plant summer squash seeds 8 inches apart, poking them into the soil 1 inch deep; water well.
            Thin seedlings to 3 feet apart. (If using transplants, set them out 3 feet apart.)
            To prevent insect damage, install protective row covers over your squash as soon as you’re done planting.
            Read The No-Spray Way to Protect Plants for more tips about using row covers.</item>

        <item>In late spring or early summer, sow seeds in warm, fertile and well-worked soil that contains
            plenty of nitrogen. Sow early sweet corn varieties one to two weeks before main season varieties
            for a longer harvest season. Many gardeners sow their early sweet corn when apple trees are in
            full bloom. Thoroughly mix in a 1-inch layer of fresh grass  clippings, compost or well-rotted
            manure along with alfalfa meal, soybean meal or another high-nitrogen organic fertilizer
            (follow label directions). Sow seeds 1 inch deep and 4 inches apart, in blocks of at least three
            rows spaced about 24 inches apart. Thin early varieties to 8 inches apart; thin taller midseason
            and late varieties to 12 inches apart.</item>

        <item>To grow sweet potatoes, begin with rooted stem cuttings, called “slips,” which sprout from the
            ends of stored tubers. If you want to grow your own slips, move parent potatoes to a warm room in
            early spring. A month before your last frost date, soak the tubers in warm water overnight, and
            then plant them sideways or diagonally in shallow containers, covering the tuber only halfway
            with sandy potting soil. After danger of frost has passed, move the sprouting sweet potatoes to
            a warm spot outdoors and keep them moist. When handled this way, stems (the slips) will emerge
            from both ends of the sweet potato, with each potato producing six or more. When the stems are
            more than 4 inches long and the weather is consistently warm, break off the slips from the parent
            sweet potatoes and plant them. \n\nSweet potatoes grow best in warm, well-drained soil with a slightly
            acidic pH between 5.6 and 6.5. Choose a site with fertile soil in full sun. Where summers are mild,
            place plastic, either black (heats soil and prevents weeds) or clear (heats more than black but does
            not control weeds), over the site in spring to warm the soil. Plant slips into small holes cut
            in the plastic, and leave plastic on the site until harvest time. Sweet potatoes benefit from a
            generous helping of fully rotted compost dug into the soil before planting, along with a light
            application of balanced organic fertilizer. Space bush-type varieties 12 inches apart, but allow
            18 inches between varieties that grow long, vigorous vines. Space rows at least 3 feet apart;
            long-vined varieties may need even more space. Situate sweet potato slips diagonally in prepared soil,
            so that only the top two leaves show at the surface.\n\n

            Water well and frequently for the first several days and be patient. After about two weeks,
            the plants should be well-rooted and showing hardy growth. For even more information on growing
            sweet potatoes, especially in cooler climates, visit Grow Sweet Potatoes – Even in the North.</item>

        <item>In spring, sow directly in the garden two weeks before your last frost date, or start seeds
            indoors three to four weeks before your last frost date and set seedlings out just as the last
            frost passes. In fall, start seeds about 10 weeks before your first frost date, and set the
            seedlings out when they are four weeks old.Prepare a rich, fertile bed by loosening the soil
            while mixing in compost and a balanced organic fertilizer, applied at label rates. Plant seeds
            half an inch deep and 3 inches apart. Set out seedlings 12 inches apart. Indoors or out, thin
            newly germinated seedlings with cuticle scissors instead of pulling them out. Chard seed capsules
            often contain two or more seeds. If more than one germinates, promptly snip off all but the
            strongest sprout at the soil line. Gradually thin direct-sown seedlings to 12 inches apart.</item>

        <item>Start seeds indoors under bright fluorescent lights in early spring, about six to eight weeks
            before your last spring frost. If kept moist and warm (above 70 degrees Fahrenheit), tomato seeds
            should sprout within a week. Transplant the seedlings to larger containers when they are about
            6 weeks old. Harden off seedlings by gradually exposing them to outdoor weather for a few hours
            each day for at least a week before transplanting them. Transplant seedlings to the garden
            (or to large containers) after your last frost has passed, during a period of warm weather.
            Choose a sunny site with fertile, well-drained  soil, and loosen the planting bed to 12 inches deep.
            Mix in a layer of mature compost. \n\nDig planting holes at least 18 inches apart, and enrich each
            with a spadeful of additional compost mixed with a balanced organic fertilizer(follow application
            rates on the fertilizer label). Plant tomatoes deeper than they grew in their containers,
            so that only the top five or six leaves show at the surface. Additional roots will grow
            from the buried section of stem.</item>


        <item>Sow a spring crop of salad turnips two  to three weeks before your last frost date; for
            a fall crop, plant seeds up to 50 days before your first fall frost. Sow all-purpose turnips
            for fall harvest 60 to 70 days before your first fall frost and sow rutabagas 100 days before
            your first fall frost. Turnips and rutabagas are good crops to plant in spaces vacated by early
            potatoes or peas, or between rows of harvested sweet corn. They grow best in fertile, well-drained
            soil with a pH between 6.0 and 7.0. Mix a light application of a balanced organic fertilizer into
            the planting bed unless ample nutrients remain in the soil from the previous crop. Loosen the soil
            to at least 12 inches deep while mixing in a half-inch layer of compost.\n\n

            Sow turnip seeds about 2 inches apart and half an inch deep. Turnips can be planted in rows spaced
            6 inches apart, or you can broadcast the seeds over the bed and pat the soil to firm them into place.
            After seeds have germinated, thin turnips to 2 inches apart. Two weeks later, when the plants reach
            4 inches tall, thin turnips (other than salad turnips) to 4 inches apart (and enjoy the greens from
            the pulled plants!). Salad turnips grow well even if spaced only 2 to 3 inches apart.\n\n

            Sow rutabaga seeds 3 inches apart and a half-inch deep, allowing at least 18 inches between rows.
            Although transplanting rutabagas isn’t usually recommended, starting seeds indoors and setting out
            week-old seedlings under shade covers is often the best way to get a good stand of rutabagas growing
            in hot summer weather. Thin direct-seeded rutabagas to at least 8 inches apart. Mulch to keep the
            soil cool and moist during hot summer weather.</item>

        <item>You should plant the least hardy grains first, followed by hardier species as the first frost
            approaches. Ten to 12 weeks before your first fall frost, start sowing seeds of oats or winter barley.
            In areas with mild winters, they can be planted up to six weeks before the first fall frost date.
            Eight to 10 weeks before your first fall frost date, sow seeds of triticale, wheat and spelt.
            (Many state extension services publish recommended dates for growing wheat, which often has a tight
            interval for seed sowing.) In areas with mild winters, you can plant these grains up to four weeks
            before the first fall frost date.\n\n
            Four to eight weeks before your first fall frost date, sow seeds of cereal rye. Cereal rye can be
            planted until the first fall frost date in areas with mild winters. All grains need fertile,
            well-drained soil and a near-neutral pH (about 6.0). If possible, sow winter grains into the stubble
            of a previous crop instead of planting into a clean bed. Any vegetation at the surface will help block
            wind and catch snow, which enhances the winter hardiness of all grains. Use a rake or hand trowel to
            rough up the soil’s surface, then plant seeds about 1 inch deep and 1 to 2 inches apart. Firmly tamp
            the seeds into place with the back of a rake, then water the area. Keep the soil lightly moist until
            the seedlings emerge.</item>

        <item>In spring, sow seeds in prepared beds or hills after your last frost has passed, or sow them
            indoors under bright fluorescent lights. Set out seedlings when they are about three weeks old.
            In Zone 6 and warmer, you can plant more winter squash in early summer, using space vacated by
            fall-planted garlic or early spring lettuce. Stop planting winter squash 14 weeks before your
            expected first fall frost. Winter squash grows best in warm conditions, in fertile, well-drained
            soil with a pH between 6.0 and 6.5. Choose a sunny site and prepare 3-foot-wide planting hills
            within wide rows, or position them along your garden’s edge. Leave 5 to 6 feet between hills.
            Loosen the soil in the planting sites to at least 12 inches deep. Thoroughly mix in a 2-inch
            layer of mature compost and a light application of balanced, organic fertilizer. Water well.
            Plant six seeds per hill, poking them into the soil 1 inch deep. After seeds germinate (about
            10 days after sowing), thin seedlings to three per hill. Set up protective row covers as soon
            as you’re done planting. (See The No-Spray Way to Protect Plants for more information on how
            to guard your garden crops with row covers.)</item>

  </string-array>






   <string-array name="Harvesting">


        <item>A month after planting, drench actively growing artichokes with a high-nitrogen liquid
            fertilizer to invigorate new growth. Artichoke plants grow 3 to 5 feet tall, and their spiny
            gray-green foliage makes them useful as edible ornamentals. As older leaves wither, gather
            them up and compost them.In mid- to late-summer, watch for upright flowering stems topped
            by artichoke flower buds. Use a sharp knife to cut globe artichokes with a 2-inch stub of
            stem attached when the lowest scales on the bud begin to open, but the top is still tight.
            Refrigerate artichokes immediately, and wash just before cooking them. After the first
            artichokes are harvested, plants typically produce a second crop of smaller buds.
            For long-term storage, you can freeze whole washed artichokes that have been steamed
            until just done.  When thawed, the artichokes can be cut in half and grilled.</item>

       <item>You can eat the young seedlings you pull while thinning your crops. As leafy types mature,
           harvest individual leaves or cut away fistfuls of greens, leaving the plants’ central crowns intact.
           New leaves will quickly replace the harvested ones. Pull whole Chinese cabbage or bok choy
           plants as you need them, and gather or protect them all before your first hard freeze. Most Asian
           greens can survive for several weeks in early winter if they’re inside a row cover or plastic tunnel.
           Whole heads that are trimmed, rinsed and refrigerated will keep for up to a month. Cut 4- to 6-inch
           stems from sprouting brassicas when the green flower buds just begin to show yellow, and promptly
           chill them in the fridge. Bumper crops of any Asian vegetables can be blanched and frozen.</item>

       <item>Controlling weeds during the first two seasons will require rigorous weeding by hand.
           Pull out weeds early and often, and mulch with hay, grass clippings or another organic material
           to suppress weeds and maintain moisture. Weeds will become less of an issue as the plants fill in.
           In early winter, after several hard freezes have damaged your asparagus fronds, cut them off
           and compost them to interrupt the life cycles of insects and diseases. Fertilize the bed with
           a 1-inch layer of rich, weed-free compost or manure topped with 3 inches of straw, rotted sawdust
           or another weed-free mulch. Clean spears will push up through the mulch in spring. Fertilize your
           asparagus again in early summer after you’ve stopped harvesting spears. You can top-dress with a
           balanced organic fertilizer, or scatter another inch of rich, weed-free compost over the decomposing
           mulch.The exact dates of your spring picking season can vary by two weeks or more because of variations
           in soil temperature from year to year. Snap off spears longer than 4 inches at the soil line as soon as
           they appear in spring. As long as a new planting grew vigorously its first season (and your growing
           season is not extremely short), you can harvest spears for two weeks after your planting is a year old.

            The next season, harvest all spears that appear for the first four weeks of active growth.
           In your third season you can harvest asparagus for six weeks, and by the fourth year the plants
           will be strong enough to tolerate a full eight-week harvest season.
            Promptly refrigerate your harvested asparagus. You can pickle, dry, or blanch and then freeze bumper crops.</item>

       <item>Harvest green beans when they are young and tender, and use two hands when picking to keep
           from breaking the brittle plants. Most bush beans will produce a second or third flush of beans
           after the first one is picked. Harvest pole beans at least twice a week to keep the plants productive.
           The mature beans of all snap bean varieties usually make good soup beans.</item>

       <item>Beets grow best when temperatures average about 65 degrees, so early plantings grow faster
           if covered with row covers. Pull weeds early and often, and use light mulches of grass clippings
           or compost to help maintain even soil moisture. Beet roots often naturally push up out of the
           ground as they mature, and this exposure to sun can cause the shoulders of white or yellow beets
           to become green and tough. Cover the roots with mulch or loose soil to ease the problem.
           Beet greens can be harvested anytime, and picking a leaf or two from each plant won’t compromise
           their root growth, but many gardeners wait until beets are ready to pull to harvest the inner leaves.
           Beet leaves taste best when they are about 6 inches long, but baby greens are wonderful in salads
           and bigger leaves still cook up nicely. Leave a few spring-sown beets in the garden through summer
           to enjoy a steady production of young greens.

            Carefully wash harvested beets in cool water. Use a sharp knife to cut off all but 1 inch of
           the beet tops, but leave the taproot intact. Removing the tops prevents moisture loss from the roots.
           Store washed, trimmed beets in your refrigerator or a cool root cellar for several months. You also
           can make  pickled beets and process them in a water bath canner for longer storage Bury mangel beets
           in a pit to use as needed for livestock fodder in winter.</item>

       <item>Mulch blackberries with 3 inches of an organic mulch year round. Chopped leaves, grass clippings,
           wood chips and sawdust are all good blackberry mulches. In spring, feed established plants with a
           balanced organic fertilizer or a topdressing of composted manure before renewing the mulch.
           In midsummer, cut off the tops of new canes at no more than 6 feet from the ground. This pruning
           triggers the growth of heavy-bearing lateral branches. In fall or early spring, prune the tips of
           these lateral branches to 12 to 18 inches long. Pruning is especially important with productive
           varieties such as ‘Nachez’ and ‘Triple Crown,’ which tend to set huge crops of small fruit when left unpruned.

            Blackberries are ready to harvest about 40 days after blooming, but most varieties taste best
           when allowed to ripen to dull black before they are picked. Harvest ripe berries in the morning
           when they are cool, and handle them carefully to avoid crushing. Refrigerate immediately. Whole
           washed blackberries, patted dry, can be frozen for later use. Blackberry juice, jams and jellies
           are easy to process in a water bath or steam canner.</item>

       <item>Pick off flowers that form on blueberry bushes their first year. (This allows plants to put
           all of their energy into getting a strong start.) Water new blueberry plantings during dry spells,
           and renew mulch as needed to maintain a 2-inch-deep layer. After plants are established, fertilize
           them in spring with a light application of a balanced organic fertilizer, or use an organic
           fertilizer labeled for acid-loving azaleas or hollies. Fertilize blueberries in late summer
           to help plants set plenty of flower buds.
            Give blueberries watering priority during droughts. Blueberry bushes have extensive surface roots,
           so watch the wetting pattern of your watering equipment to ensure a thorough soaking to 6 inches deep.
           Learning how to grow blueberries involves employing proper pruning technique and balancing new growth
           with old. Pruning is essential to keep production high, plants at a manageable height and berry size
           large. Healthy highbush blueberries and rabbiteyes should produce at least one new cane each year,
           but there may be more. In late winter, count the number of new canes and cut off an equal number of
           old ones at ground level. Cut back the tips of the new canes to encourage branching, and snip out
           dead branches and low limbs that would touch the ground if fruit-laden. If you don’t see any new canes,
           step up fertilization and check the soil pH.Blueberries taste best if they stay on the plant for a few
           days after they turn blue. Pick blueberries at least twice a week while they are ripe. Choose a mix of
           early- and late-maturing varieties to have fresh blueberries for more than a month.</item>

       <item>Harvest broccoli heads when the florets around the edges of the head begin to show slight
           loosening, but when the beads in most of the crown are still tight. Cut the stems at an angle
           — this will keep water from pooling inside the cut stem and causing rot. Refrigerate the cut
           heads immediately. To get top home-preserved quality, steam-blanch broccoli before freezing it.
           Continue to water the plants after harvest, as most varieties will produce secondary heads.

        Watch broccoli raab closely, and harvest just as the first flowers show their yellow petals.
           Sprouting broccoli and broccoli raab are also cut-and-come-again crops that produce a second
           flush of buds after the first ones have been harvested.
        When plants are spaced 18 inches apart, average yields are about 1 pound of broccoli per foot of row.
           Three to four plants per person is sufficient for fresh summer eating, but you should triple that number
           if you want a freezer crop for winter.</item>

       <item>Featherweight row cover held aloft with hoops or  stakes is the easiest way to protect Brussels
           sprout plants from grasshoppers and other summer insects. When the plants are 12 inches tall,
           top-dress them with a high nitrogen organic fertilizer such as composted manure.
            As plants grow, stake plants to keep them from falling over. Upright Brussels sprout plants
           produce better than crooked ones. To harvest, twist off sprouts, a few at a time, as soon as
           they are at least one-half inch in diameter. Keep in mind that the first sprouts are often much
           smaller than those produced later in the season. Breaking off the lowest leaves gives nearby sprouts more room to grow.
            Refrigerate harvested sprouts immediately. Brussels sprouts will keep in the refrigerator for
           several weeks, or they can be blanched and frozen. Here’s another neat storage option: In the North
           where the plants grow quite large, they can be pulled from the garden with sprouts still attached,
           stripped of their leaves, and stuck into a bucket of damp sand kept in a cold root cellar.
            As biennials, Brussels sprouts produce yellow flowers followed by elongated seedpods in their second year.
           When the seedpods dry to tan, gather them in a paper bag, and allow them to dry indoors for a week.
           Shatter the dry pods and collect the largest seeds for replanting. Under good conditions, Brussels
           sprouts seeds will store up to three years.</item>

       <item>Begin harvesting cabbage when the heads feel firm, using a sharp knife to cut the heads from the stem.
           Remove and compost rough outer leaves, and promptly refrigerate harvested heads. If cut high, many varieties
           will produce several smaller secondary heads from the roots and crown left behind.
            Cabbage will store in the refrigerator for two weeks or more, and you can keep your fall crop in cool
           storage for several months. Clean cabbage carefully, because heads may harbor hidden insects.
            Cabbage yield is generally about 1 pound per foot of row. For the spring crop, three cabbage plants
           per person is probably sufficient for fresh eating. Grow another four plants per person in fall if you
           plan to store your cabbage or make sauerkraut.</item>

       <item>Prepare the planting bed by loosening the soil to at least 12 inches deep. Thoroughly mix in a 1-inch
           layer of mature compost or a half-inch layer of vermicompost (carrots love what earthworms leave behind).
           Sow your seeds about a quarter inch deep and 2 inches apart, in rows spaced at least 10 inches apart;
           carrots do well in double or triple rows. Thin seedlings to 4 to 6 inches apart, depending on the variety’s
           mature size.Pull or dig spring-sown carrots when roots reach mature size and show rich color. Taste improves
           as carrots mature, but do not leave mature carrots in warm soil any longer than necessary (many critters like carrots).
           Summer-sown carrots that mature in cool fall soil can be left in the ground longer, but should be
           dug before the ground freezes to preserve their quality. Remove tops to prevent moisture loss, rinse clean,
           and store in a refrigerator or cold root cellar. Most varieties keep for several months in the fridge.
           Carrots also may be canned, pickled, dried or frozen.</item>

       <item>Featherweight row cover held aloft with hoops or stakes is the easiest way to protect actively
           growing cauliflower plants from grasshoppers and other summer insects.

            As the plants grow, drench them with a high nitrogen fertilizer such as fish emulsion every two weeks.
           Cauliflower plants stay low to the ground, and never grow tall. Use a sharp knife to cut heads from the plants
            when they are the size you want, but before they become off-color or rice-like in texture.
           Refrigerate harvested cauliflower immediately. Cauliflower will keep in the refrigerator for several weeks,
           or you can blanch and freeze the florets. Cauliflower plants produce only one head, so they can be pulled
           and composted after the crop has been harvested. </item>

       <item>Celery and celeriac seedlings should show vigorous new growth a few weeks after they have been
           transplanted. Plants that are making little progress should be drenched with fish emulsion or
           another organic liquid fertilizer. Try to keep the plants’ roots moist at all times, and don’t
           worry about excessive rain — celery and celeriac tolerate waterlogged soil better than other vegetables.
           To encourage stalk celery to develop a pale, mild-flavored heart, use an elastic hair scrunchie or
           strips of soft cloth to secure the stalks into a bunch after the plants have been growing in the
           garden for eight to 10 weeks. Blanching — excluding light from the stalks to prevent chlorophyll
           production — for one to two weeks is necessary to grow celery that looks lighter and tastes milder.
           Cut high, 1 to 2 inches from the ground, when harvesting celery hearts. A new stalk (and sometimes two or three)
           will sprout from the stump left behind. Trim off excess leaves and tough outer stalks before storing
           celery in the refrigerator. Freeze blemished celery and the outside stalks that are dark and coarse
           for flavoring broths and stocks. Include bits of celery or cutting celery in packets of frozen garden veggies.
           Blanch and dry a bumper crop of stalk celery or cutting celery. Dried celery makes a great addition to homemade soup mixes.

            Celeriac plants shed their lowest, oldest leaves naturally beginning in midsummer. Low, hollow stems
           in good condition can even be used as novel drinking straws. Harvest celeriac before hard freezes damage
           the roots. Clip off all leaves and roots before storing celeriac in the refrigerator or packed in damp
           sand in your root cellar.</item>

       <item>Cucumbers self-regulate how many fruits they carry at a time. To maximize production, harvest
           fruits as soon as they reach picking size. Pick daily, be­cause under ideal conditions, cucumber
           fruits can double in size in just one day. Use scissors or small shears to snip fruits with a short
           stub of stem attached. Lightly scrub, pat dry and refrigerate harvested cucumbers right away.

            Depending on variety and size of the fruit, one cucumber plant will typically bear 10 to 20 fruits,
           which would total about 2 to 3 pounds. Apound of cu­cumbers yields about a pint of pickles, and six
           healthy plants of a pickling va­riety will produce enough cucumbers in one season to make more than
           a dozen pints of pickles.</item>

       <item>Harvest beans and peas for drying anytime after the pods have become leathery up to when they
           have dried to their mature colors. (For example, the pods of ‘Dwarf Horticultural’ beans turn ivory
           with red stripes when the seeds inside reach maturity, while the pods of ‘Pinkeye Purple Hull’ cowpeas
           turn dark purple.) You can harvest green beans and peas for fresh cooking sooner, but seeds you intend
           to store must be fully ripe.

            Leave drying pods on the plants as long as you can, but harvest them before a period of prolonged
           rain. If damp weather sets in just when your beans should be drying, pull up the plants and hang them
           upside down in a dry place until the beans are dry enough to pick and sort. Collect drying pods from pole
           varieties and runner beans as they change to tan or brown, and let the pods dry until crisp in a shallow
           tray or box kept indoors.

           Threshing, or “shelling,” is the process of removing bean seeds from the pods, and you can do it
           either by machine or by hand. On a home-garden scale, shell a large crop of dry beans or peas by
           placing the dry pods on a tarp and crushing them by walking over them. Gather the heavy seeds that
           drop from the pods, and remove debris by pouring the beans back and forth from one bowl into another
           in front of a fan for a few minutes. Another option for small harvests is to put the pods in a pillowcase,
           tie the pillowcase closed tightly, and tumble it in a warm (not hot) clothes dryer.

           After shelling and winnowing out debris, place your beans or peas in open bowls, and let them dry
           at room temperature for two weeks, stirring often. When the seeds are hard and glossy, remove any
           shriveled beans (dumping the beans over a screen can help), and store your sorted beans in airtight
           containers. If you suspect bean weevils or other insects may be present in your stored beans or peas,
           keep the sealed containers in the freezer. </item>

       <item>Another way to keep pesky flea beetles at bay is to grow eggplant in containers. Compact
           eggplant varieties work especially well in pots. Keep your eggplants on an outdoor table to
           keep them out of range of ground-dwelling flea beetles. Plants produce best in 16-inch-wide
           pots or planters. Dark-colored pots help accumulate heat in cool climates. Growing eggplant
           in containers requires fertilizing as often as needed to maintain steady growth and good leaf
           color. Plants that need to be watered often also need to be fed more frequently.Begin harvesting
           eggplant when the fruits reac full size and pressing firmly produces a thumbprint that bounces
           back quickly. Under-ripe eggplants are too hard to take a thumbprint, and overripe ones are so
           soft that a thumbprint leaves a permanent bruise. Eggplant skins should be tender and glossy.
           Use pruning shears to harvest eggplants with their cap (calyx) intact. Storing eggplant is easy
           — simply keep the fruit at cool room temperature or in the refrigerator for no more than three
           days before cooking or preserving.</item>

       <item>Keep bulb fennel seedlings carefully weeded, and drench plants with a liquid organic
           fertilizer when they are 12 inches tall. In early summer, mulch bulb fennel with grass clippings
           or another organic mulch to retain soil moisture, an essential factor in growing big, crisp bulbs.
           However, mulching too early can delay soil warming and invite problems with slugs. When growing
           fennel, do not allow the plants to run dry once bulb formation has begun.

            Begin harvesting fennel bulbs as you can use them in the kitchen after the bulbs are more than
           2 inches across. Bulb fennel plants grown in spring do not get extremely large, and should be
           harvested before the weather turns hot. If you cut the bulb high, so that the root and the base
           of the bulb remain in the soil, the stub will regrow a couple of small crowns with miniature
           fennel fronds — nice little tidbits to include in packets of frozen garden veggie mixtures.

           With half of their tops trimmed off, fennel bulbs will keep in plastic bags in the refrigerator
           for a couple of weeks. Excess bulb fennel can be blanched and frozen. </item>

       <item>Allow new figs to grow freely their first year. In early winter, select three to five strong,
           widely spaced branches, and prune out all others close to the ground. As long as the selected
           branches are not damaged by winter cold, they will bear a light crop in early summer, and a heavier one a few weeks later.

            Each spring, feed established plants with a balanced organic fertilizer or a topdressing
           of composted manure before renewing the mulch.Pruning fig plants is best done in spring, after
           surviving buds have begun to grow. Pruning figs back to live wood is often necessary in Zone 7,
           where plants are occasionally frozen back to the roots. In other areas, prune to thin plants back
           to about five strong branches, and to remove old and damaged wood.
            Figs change colors and soften as they become ripe. Taste-test sample fruits often, because
           ripe figs do not hold well on the plants in hot weather.

            Wear gloves and long sleeves when picking figs, because the plants’ sap can irritate your skin.
           Refrigerate your harvest immediately. For long-term storage, figs can be dried, frozen, or canned
           in syrup using a water bath or steam canner.</item>

       <item>Pruning is a key aspect of growing fruit trees. The goal of pruning fruit trees is to provide
           the leaves and fruit access to light and fresh air. The ideal branching pattern varies with species,
           and some apple and pear trees can be pruned and trained into fence- or wall-hugging espaliers to
           save space. Begin pruning fruit trees to shape them in their first year, and then prune annually
           in late winter, before the buds swell. Pruning a little too much questionable growth is better
           than removing too little.

            Many fruit trees set too much fruit, and the excess should be thinned. Asian pear trees should
           have 70 percent of their green fruits snipped off when the pears are the size of a dime, and
           apples should be thinned to 6 inches apart before the fruits are the size of a quarter. When any
           type of fruit tree is holding a heavy crop, thinning some of the green fruits will increase fruit
           size, reduce limb breakage and help prevent alternative bearing (a tree setting a crop only every
           other year).With the exception of pears, tree fruits should be harvested just as they approach
           full ripeness and then kept chilled to slow spoilage. The flavor of most apples improves after
           a few weeks in cold storage, so a second refrigerator or a root cellar may be useful. Apples and
           pears can be kept for several months in a refrigerator, but softer stone fruits (cherries, nectarines,
           peaches and plums) must be canned, dried, frozen or juiced within a few days of harvest for long-term storage.</item>

       <item>From early summer to midsummer, watch plants closely and pull them when about one-third
           of the leaves appear pale and withered. Use a digging fork to loosen the soil before pulling the plants.
           Handle the newly pulled bulbs delicately to avoid bruising them. Lay the whole plants out to dry in a warm,
           airy spot that is protected from rain and direct sun. After a week or so, brush off soil from the bulbs
           with your hands, and use pruning shears to clip roots to half an inch long. Wait another week before
           clipping off the stems of hardneck varieties or trimming and braiding softnecks into clusters. Do not
           remove the papery outer wrappers, as these inhibit sprouting and protect the cloves from rotting.

            Storage life varies with variety and with growing and storage conditions. When kept at 50 to 60 degrees
           Fahrenheit, rocamboles store about four months, other hardneck garlic varieties usually last six months,
           and softneck and elephant garlic store for eight months or more. Hang your cured crop in mesh bags, or
           braid softneck types and suspend from rafters in a cool basement or garage.</item>

       <item>Matching your trellis design and pruning practices to the natural growth habit of your chosen
           grapes will go a long way toward preventing disease and maximizing productivity. In general,
           ‘Concord’ grapes and other labrusca varieties produce downward-facing branches from long canes
           that form a cascade of foliage, so they do best on a high trellis or an arbor. Similarly,
           muscadine grapes are easiest to manage on an overhead rectangular trellis, sometimes called an “X trellis.”
           With these vigorous fruits, pruning should be geared toward preserving two to four 6-foot
           canes while trimming out excess growth.

            Most table and wine grapes produce upward-facing shoots, so a two-tiered trellis that supports
           the branches as they gain height is best. Trellises of tightly woven wire are preferable because
           they do a good job of supporting the vines when they become heavy with fruit. Pruning of table and
           wine grapes should be aggressive — remove all old growth except for selected fruiting spurs.
           If you’re growing table grapes on an arbor, you can prune a little less if you want to get a
           thick cover of foliage.

            Prune grapes in late winter, before the buds begin to swell. The first year after planting,
           concentrate on helping your young plants grow straight, sturdy trunks. The training of side
           branches will begin in the second year, with buds ready to bear fruit three years after planting.
           Each grape variety you grow will respond differently to various pruning practices, so be prepared
           to fine-tune your methods.Grapes are ripe when they taste sweet. Early-maturing white or red varieties
           may be ready to pick a month before later-maturing blue or black grapes. Allow grapes to stay on the
           vine until the berries show a whitish bloom on their skins, but bring them in should a period of wet
           weather be in the forecast. Ripe grapes often crack after heavy rains.

            Keep clusters of unwashed grapes in the refrigerator, stored in plastic bags to help retain humidity.
           Fresh or frozen grapes can be made into juice, jelly or wine. Seedless grapes are easiest to dry into raisins.</item>

       <item>Allow upright horseradish plants a full season to establish themselves in the garden.
           The long, strap-like leaves often grow 3 to 4 feet tall; they should not be fed to livestock or
           people, but make good compost fodder. Remove weeds that crowd the young plants. Growing horseradish
           plants develop most of their storage roots in early fall, so they should not be allowed to run dry in late summer.

            Overwintered horseradish plants may send up spikes of white flowers in late spring. Clip off the
           seed heads before they become fully mature, because horseradish easily becomes weedy.Your horseradish
           harvest should commence in late fall, after several frosts have damaged the leaves. Use a digging fork
           to loosen the soil on two sides of the plant, gathering up broken pieces of root as you dig. Then loosen
           the soil on the other side of the plant before attempting to pull it. Set aside or replant root pieces
           the size of a pencil, and store others in plastic bags in the refrigerator. Harvesting horseradish can
           continue into winter provided the ground is not frozen — or, you can dig the roots first thing in spring.
           Between diggings, keep fresh horseradish roots in the fridge, ready to use.

            To prepare fresh horseradish for eating, peel a root and cut it into small pieces, then puree in a food
           processor with just enough water for chopping. Add a few pinches of salt and a teaspoon or two of white
           vinegar, and puree until only slightly lumpy. Place in a small clean jar, and add more vinegar if needed
           to cover the horseradish. Use within two weeks by mixing with mayo or sour cream to make horseradish sauce.</item>

        <item>Cool soil temperatures improve flavor and texture. If your winters are cold, begin digging Jerusalem
            artichokes in late fall, at least two weeks after your first hard freeze. In milder areas, wait until
            midwinter to dig your tubers.

            Using a digging fork, start at one end of the bed and work your way across, feeling for tubers with your
            fingers. Tubers can sometimes be hiding a foot deep. Harvesting can continue through winter as long as the
            ground isn’t frozen. In very cold climates, digging will often have to wait until the soil thaws in spring.

            Rinse and pat dry harvested tubers before storing them in a refrigerator or cool root cellar. Jerusalem
            artichokes will keep in the fridge for a couple of months.</item>


        <item>Begin harvesting when plants’ leaves are larger than your hand, and just break off the older, bigger
            leaves as you need them for cooking. New leaves will continue to grow from the plants’ centers. After the
            plants reach harvestable size, most varieties will yield three leaves per plant every five days.

            Leaf quality is best in the fall, after the plants have been exposed to a few light frosts. These are
            the best leaves to blanch and freeze for long-term storage. Kale and collard greens also can be dried
            into snackable chips.</item>

       <item>In spring, you may need to protect kohlrabi from cold winds with cloches or a tunnel covered with
           row cover or perforated plastic. Featherweight row cover held aloft with hoops or stakes is the
           easiest way to protect actively growing kohlrabi from insects. Should the little plants refuse to
           grow even after the soil warms up in spring, drench them with a high-nitrogen fertilizer, such as
           fish emulsion, every two weeks.Pull up entire plants when kohlrabi bulbs reach 3 inches in diameter.
           Cut off the roots and leaves and store the bulbs in your refrigerator. Kohlrabi will keep in the
           refrigerator for several weeks, or you can blanch and freeze uniform chunks of peeled kohlrabi.

            Some people enjoy eating the young leaves taken from the tops of kohlrabi as cooked greens,
           especially in fall when the leaves tend to be sweet and tender. This is seldom true of leaves
           taken from kohlrabi that has grown in warm weather. </item>

        <item>Keep leeks carefully weeded, and drench plants with a liquid organic fertilizer when they
            are 15 inches tall. In dry climates, mulch leeks with grass clippings, chopped leaves or another
            organic mulch that helps retain soil moisture. Leeks need more water than other garden crops,
            and should never be allowed to run dry.Use a digging fork to loosen soil around leeks before
            pulling them as needed in the kitchen. Trim roots to one-half inch, and cut off all but 2 inches
            of the green tops. Store in plastic bags in the refrigerator for up to two weeks. Before eating,
            slice leeks lengthwise and rinse under cool running water to remove bits of soil. Excess leeks are
            easy to dry in a food dehydrator.</item>

        <item>Harvest lettuce in the morning, after the plants have had all night to plump up with water.
            Wilted lettuce picked on a hot day seldom revives, even when rushed to the refrigerator. Pull
            (and eat) young plants until you get the spacing you want. Gather individual leaves or use
            scissors to harvest handfuls of baby lettuce. Rinse lettuce thoroughly with cool water, shake
            or spin off excess moisture, and store it in plastic bags in the refrigerator. Lettuce often
            needs a second cleaning as it is prepared for the table.</item>

        <item>Most muskmelons naturally separate (“slip”) from the vine when ripe, which means you can pick
            these melons with just a gentle tug. The rinds of some varieties of honeydew and watermelon change
            color when ripe, making it easier to learn the melon-picker’s art. Watermelons are ripe when the
            curled tendril nearest to the melon dries to brown, and when the melon sounds deep and solid if
            thumped. Pecking from birds often indicates imminent ripeness.

            Keep muskmelons at room temperature for two to three days after harvesting to help bring out flavors
            , and then move them to a refrigerator. Always keep honeydew and Asian melons in the refrigerator.
            Watermelons stored in a cool place (about 55 degrees Fahrenheit) will keep for several weeks.</item>


        <item>Weed by hand for the first few weeks after planting okra. After the soil becomes summer-warm,
            install a soaker hose down the row and cover it with a mulch of grass clippings or wood chips.
            During dry periods, deeply soak the bed once per week.

            After the first big harvest of pods, top-dress the plants with a balanced organic fertilizer,
            gently mixed into the top half-inch of soil. After fertilizing, water thoroughly with a hose
            to soak the fertilizer into the soil.You can begin harvesting okra three to four days after each
            flower fades. After plants start blossoming, pods should be harvested every other day. Use pruning
            shears or a sharp knife to gather pods with a small stub of stem attached. Pods more than 5 inches
            long may be tough, though long-podded varieties often produce pods that stay tender to 8 inches long.
            Immediately refrigerate pods after harvesting okra, and wait until just before cooking to rinse
            clean and pat dry.

            For long-term storage, whole pods can be pickled, steamed and frozen, or, for frying later,
            cut into slices, tossed in seasoned corn meal, and frozen.</item>


       <item>The tops of bulb onion plants fall over naturally once the bulbs have matured. When half of the tops
           in a planting have fallen over, lift all of the bulbs and place the pulled plants in a warm, dry place
           away from direct sunshine to cure.
            Cure short-day onions for just a few days before clipping off roots and tops and storing the onions
           in the refrigerator. Cure intermediate- and long-day onions for two to three weeks. When the onions feel
           paper-dry on the outside, clip off tops and roots, and lightly brush off loose soil before storing the
           onions in a cool, dry place. Arrange them in a single layer or hang them in mesh bags. Properly cured
           onions will store for six to eight months in a root cellar or cool basement. Check them weekly to sniff
           out signs of spoilage.</item>

        <item>Parsnips demand constant weeding for several weeks, but then the plants produce long, celery-like
            leaves that shade surrounding soil. Water as often as needed to keep soil constantly moist. In dry
            climates, mulch growing parsnips with grass clippings, chopped leaves or another organic mulch that
            helps retain soil moisture. Parsnips need more water than other garden crops, and should never be
            allowed to run dry.Like carrots, parsnips push up out of the ground
            when they reach mature size. Use a digging fork to loosen the soil around parsnips before pulling
            them as needed in the kitchen. Immediately cut off the tops and wash and refrigerate parsnips, which
            will store in plastic bags in the refrigerator for up to two months.
            In fall, many gardeners leave some of their parsnips in the ground, and harvest them as soon as
            new growth appears in early spring. </item>

        <item>Keep your actively growing peanuts thoroughly weeded, and hill up loose soil around the plants
            when they are 12 inches tall. About six weeks after planting, peanut plants produce pea-like yellow
            flowers on stems that grow longer each day. When fertilized, the flowers become pegs that bend over
            until their tips penetrate the soil. Peanuts develop underground, at the ends of these pegs.

            You should wait to harvest your peanuts until the plants begin to die back and the soil is warm and dry.
            Loosen the soil with a digging fork, and then use two hands to lift intact peanut plants with stems and
            roots attached.

            After harvesting peanuts, shake off the soil and lay the plants in the sun to dry. Let the harvested
            plants dry in the sun for a week, and then pick off the nuts and let them dry indoors for two more weeks.
            Many people use movable carts to cure peanuts, so they can be dried outdoors on sunny days, and moved
            to shelter before forecasted rain.

            Peanuts are a relatively good storage crop. Dry, unshelled peanuts will store in a cool, dry place for
            several months. For long-term storage, shelled raw peanuts can be stored in the freezer. </item>


        <item>To avoid mangling the vines, use two hands to  harvest peas. When green peas are ripe, harvest
            them daily, preferably in the morning. Pick snow peas when the pods reach full size and the peas
            inside are just beginning to swell. For best flavor and yields, allow snap peas to change from flat
            to plump before picking them. Gather sweet green shell peas when the pods begin to show a waxy sheen,
            but before their color fades. Immediately refrigerate picked peas to stop the conversion of sugar to
            starches and maintain the peas’ crisp texture. Promptly blanch and freeze your extra peas.

            Soup peas can be left on the vines until the pods dry to tan. After shelling and sorting, allow soup
            peas to dry at room temperature until they are so hard that they shatter when struck with a hammer.
            Store in airtight containers in a cool, dry place.</item>

        <item>You can eat peppers when they are mature yet still green (green peppers), although the flavor and
            the vitamin content of peppers improve as they ripen to red, yellow or orange. Use pruning shears to
            snip ripe peppers from the plant, leaving a small stub of stem attached. Bumper crops can be briefly
            steam-blanched or roasted and then frozen, either whole (for stuffing) or chopped. Peppers are also
            easy to dry. Dried peppers quickly plump if soaked in hot water, or you can grind them into powders
            for your spice shelf.</item>

        <item>Potato plants die back as they finish making their crop. Begin digging when the foliage starts to
            yellow and wither. Gently knock off dirt and allow the tubers to dry indoors, covered with dry towels,
            for a day or two. Take care to protect the tubers from sunlight at all times to prevent greening that
            may result in bitterness. Store the most perfect tubers in a cool, 50- to 60- degree place to be used
            as seed potatoes. Eat the “less than perfect” potatoes first, but keep in mind that they won’t store forever.
            For longer storage, potato slices can be blanched and dried. A pressure canner must be used to can potatoes.</item>

        <item>Pumpkins are ripe when you can’t easily pierce the rind with your fingernail. Try to delay harvest
            until the vines begin to die back. Use pruning shears to cut pumpkins from the vine, leaving at least
            1 inch of stem attached. Wipe fruits clean with a damp cloth, and then cure your pumpkins in a 70- to 80-degree
            Fahrenheit area for two weeks. Store cured pumpkins in a cool, dry place, such as a basement or garage.
            Thin-skinned pumpkin varieties (such as ‘Winter Luxury’) and oilseed pumpkins will store for only a few weeks,
            but some moschata pumpkins will keep for six months or more.</item>

        <item>When pulling radishes in warm weather, cool them right away by dropping them into a pail of cold water.
            Use a sharp knife or kitchen shears to remove the leaves, then store in the refrigerator for up to three weeks.
            Large oriental varieties can be left in the ground well into fall and dug just before the soil freezes.

            Harvest salad radishes once they are bigger than grapes. Radishes left in the ground too long develop a pithy
            texture and often crack following heavy rains.

            Hot weather and drought encourage the development of spicy flavor compounds, which are similar to those
            found in horseradish.</item>

        <item>In late summer, pinch back new cane tips at 4 to 5 feet to stimulate the growth of heavy-bearing lateral
            branches. This type of pruning is especially effective for pushing summer red raspberries and black and purple
            raspberries to develop more buds. You can tip-prune everbearing raspberries in midsummer to encourage a heavier
            fall crop, but doing so isn’t necessary.
            When a raspberry cane finishes producing fruit, it naturally dies. To keep a clean patch with good air and
            sun penetration, remove old canes by clipping them off at the ground and pulling them out from the top.
            Frequently with everbearing raspberries, the tip end of a cane will fruit in fall, and buds farther down the
            stem that survive winter will bear a summer crop. Prune off the spent tip, but harvest the summer crop before
            removing the cane.Raspberries are ripe when they show good color and come off easily when picked. Daily
            harvesting is best, because hot sun can scald ripe berries and prolonged rains can cause them to rot.

            Harvest raspberries into shallow containers, no more than three berries deep. Refrigerate picked berries
            immediately. Wait until you are preparing to eat or freeze raspberries to rinse them clean with cool water.
            To freeze, pat the rinsed berries dry with a clean towel and arrange them in a shallow pan covered with waxed
            paper. Place in the freezer for an hour, then transfer the frozen berries to freezer-safe containers. You can
            use fresh or frozen raspberries to make jams, syrups, or batches of raspberry lemonade or homemade wine.</item>

        <item>Instead of seeds you should buy rhubarb plants, which won’t cost much because you need only a few. As a
            general rule, allow only one plant per person in your household unless you have space to spare for these big plants,
            which mature to 4 to 5 feet across.

            Planting rhubarb is best done in spring, around your last frost date. Plant in moist, fertile soil in full
            sun to partial afternoon shade, but note that rhubarb plants can be moved at other times of the year if soil
            is kept packed around their roots. Space plants 4 to 5 feet apart, or use them as a focal points dotted around
            your garden’s boundary. Enrich planting holes generously with compost as well as a standard application of a
            balanced organic fertilizer when planting rhubarb.

            In late winter, rake up and compost old mulch and plant debris from your rhubarb patch, and scatter a balanced
            organic fertilizer over the soil. Top the site off with a thick organic mulch that will deter weeds until the
            plants leaf out. Pruned tops from large ornamental grasses are seasonally available and useful for this purpose.
            In late spring, after the plants show vigorous growth, watch for the emergence of huge flower clusters, and cut
            them off to keep plants from expending energy producing flowers and unwanted seeds. A year after planting, harvest
            two to three rhubarb stalks per plant weekly in late spring by twisting them away from the base. In subsequent seasons
            , harvest all the stalks you want for six weeks in late spring, and then allow the plants to grow freely.

            In many years, rhubarb plants may struggle through summer hot spells to the point of near collapse, and then produce
            lovely new stems in late summer and fall. Late summer rhubarb is infinitely edible.

            After harvesting, top off stalks to remove rhubarb leaves. Cut the rhubarb stalks into uniform length, and store
            in plastic bags in the refrigerator. Before cooking, remove long strings as you would from celery.</item>


        <item>Keep shallots carefully weeded, and drench plants with a liquid organic fertilizer when they are 12 inches tall.
            Shallot plants naturally splay out as they approach maturity, as each plant will have divided into several separate
            plantlets. Shallots grown from cloves may produce a dozen or more small bulbs, while seed-sown varieties typically
            produce three perfect shallots per plant.Begin harvesting shallots when the tops are actively dying back, which is
            usually late summer. Loosen the soil around the plants with a digging fork, pull up the plants and shake off the soil.

            After harvesting shallots, cure the plants in a warm, well-ventilated place for a week, and then trim back the tops
            to 4 inches, and clip off the roots. Continue curing for two more weeks before trimming again and cleaning up for storage.
            Store cured shallots indoors, in a cool, dry place.</item>

        <item>Keep weeds under control until developing sorghu plants are big enough to dominate their space. Six weeks
            after planting, drench sorghum with a high-nitrogen liquid fertilizer to invigorate new growth. Many grain
            sorghum varieties grow to only 5 feet tall, but sweet sorghum and broom corn plants can top 8 feet.Like corn,
            grains of sorghum go through an immature “milk” stage when a pierced kernel will bleed a milk-like juice.
            Sweet sorghum is harvested about two weeks after the milk stage by cutting off the canes at ground level,
            stripping off the leaves, and setting aside the green canes. The ground, pressed canes yield a sweet, light
            green juice that is then cooked into sorghum syrup. The barely-mature seeds can be fed to animals, or cooked
            and eaten like other whole grains.

            Grain sorghum and broom corn are harvested later, after the seeds are fully mature, with hard glossy seed coats.
            Harvest grain sorghum by cutting off the seed clusters with a few inches of stalk attached, and dry them in a warm,
            well-ventilated place for at least a week. Roll the dried seed heads over a hardware cloth screen to free the seeds,
            and then winnow out plant debris and store your processed harvest in the freezer.

            When the seeds of broom corn are hard and the plants begin to fail, cut stalks as long as you want them for
            decorating or crafting purposes. Allow the stalks to dry in small bunches.</item>

        <item>Allow seedlings of garden sorrel or French sorrel a full season to establish themselves in the garden.
            Remove weeds that crowd your growing sorrel plants.
            Except for the ‘Profusion’ variety, sorrel plants send up flowering spikes which eventually adorn themselves with
            thousands of dangling flat seeds. Clip off the seed heads while they are still green, because sorrel can
            become weedy in many climates. Sorrel is closely related to the weed called yellow dock (R. crispus) and
            shares its talent for reseeding.Sorrel is usually eaten raw in salads or on sandwiches, or cooked into
            creamy sorrel soup. In any dish, a little sorrel goes a long way. Only one or two leaves, slipped into a
            sandwich or sliced into thin ribbons and tossed into a salad, are plenty. The citrusy, sour tang of sorrel
            leaves make them a great accent herb for Thai-inspired dishes. If you are hooked on sorrel soup, you can
            steam sorrel leaves and form them into cigar-shaped rolls before freezing them.</item>

       <item>Prepare the planting bed by loosening the soil at least 10 inches deep. Thoroughly mix in compost along
           with alfalfa meal, soybean meal or another high-nitrogen organic fertilizer (follow label directions).
           Sow seeds a half-inch deep and 2 inches apart, in rows spaced at least 8 inches apart. As the plants grow,
           gradually thin them so the leaves of neighboring plants barely overlap.Beginning about six weeks after planting,
           pinch off individual leaves as you need them in the kitchen, leaving the central rosette intact.

            In spring, long, warm days cause spinach to “bolt” (flower and produce seeds). Unless you plan to save seeds,
           pull up the plants when you notice them developing a tall central stem. Thoroughly clean, then steam-blanch
           (which limits their uptake of water and fixes enzymes) and freeze bumper crops.</item>

        <item>Growing stevia is easy in well-drained beds or large containers, and the leaves can be dried for winter
            use like any other herb. Stevia grows best in warm conditions similar to those preferred by basil. Plants
            grown in warm climates will grow to 24 inches tall and wide. Where summers are cool, expect stevia plants
            to grow up to 16 inches. Grow three to five plants for a year’s supply of dried stevia leaves.

            Stevia can be started from seed indoors in late winter, but it’s best to grow it from rooted cuttings.
            Germination of stevia seeds tends to be spotty, so keep seed-sown plants under bright lights until the
            weather warms in spring. Look for stevia plants in the herbs section at garden centers, or locate mail-order
            suppliers using our Seed and Plant Finder.

            Choose a well-drained site, and set out the plants 2 feet apart after your last frost. Be sure to choose an
            accessible spot, because you will need to gather stems often. Where summers are extremely hot, stevia benefits
            from slight afternoon shade. Elsewhere, grow stevia in full sun.


            Left unpruned, stevia will grow into a lanky, upright plant that produces tiny white flowers in late summer.
            To maximize leaf production, you must trim back the plants several times to induce branching, first when plants
            are about 8 inches tall, and again in early summer. You can use the leaves from the pinched-back stem tips, or
            root them in moist potting soil to increase your supply of stevia plants.In most areas, you can harvest stevia in
            midsummer by cutting back the plants by half their size, and again in early fall when new growth slows to a
            standstill. Stevia can be dried in bunches like other herbs, but you will get better quality by drying it in a
            dehydrator or a 150-degree- Fahrenheit oven until crisp. Store dried stevia leaves in an airtight container in a
            cool, dark place. Wait until you’re ready to use stevia leaves to crush them.</item>


         <item>Following spring planting, pick off flowers that form on June-bearing varieties their first season. With
                ever-bearing varieties (especially alpines), pinching off the first flowers can lead to better production of
                later-ripening, more intensely flavored fruits. With vigorous varieties, pinch off about half of the runners
                to help the mother plants concentrate on the following year’s crop.

            If you don’t need more plants, removing all runners from ever-bearing varieties will increase the production of big, juicy berries.

            Renovate beds of June-bearing strawberries in summer, after the fruiting season has ended. Pull weeds, and thin
             plants to 6 inches apart. Mow or cut back old leaves 4 inches from the ground and distribute a light application
             of a balanced organic fertilizer between the plants. Top the renovated bed with a half-inch of weed-free compost
             or fertile garden soil. Handled this way, a planting of 25 June-bearing strawberry plants grown in a 30-square-foot
             bed will produce about 25 quarts (close to 30 pounds) of strawberries annually for three to four years.

            Most strawberries produce runners, which can be trained to take root in promising places. Lift and move wanderers
             in late summer or first thing in spring. Varieties that do not produce runners can be divided and replanted, preferably
             in early spring.Expect some flavor variation each season. Cool, wet springs lead to soft, watery berries, while plenty
             of warm sun brings about firmer, sweeter fruits.

            Pick strawberries with a short stub of green stem attached. Harvest in the cool of the morning and refrigerate right away.
             Wait until just before eating or preserving strawberries to wash them under cool running water and remove their green caps.
             Preserve berries within three days for optimal flavor and color.</item>

        <item>Most summer grain crops require close monitoring as the seeds approach ripeness. Tap brown buckwheat seed
            clusters to see whether any black mature seeds fall free. Corn and pearl millet should be left on the plants
            to dry as long as dry weather allows. With sunflowers, eager visits by birds will be an indicator that the
            seeds are ripe. When any grain crop is almost ripe and a prolonged spell of rainy weather is in the forecast,
            the best strategy is to harvest the crop and allow it to dry in a sheltered, well-ventilated place. Use a fan
            if necessary. Summer grains are tough, resilient plants, but an extended period of rain that leads to moldy seeds
            is the worst thing that can happen to any homestead grain.

            Harvested grains should be stored in rodent-proof containers, such as garbage cans with secure lids. Store corn
            ears intact, and wait until just before cracking or milling to twist off the kernels.

            Collect the large seeds that fall from dry sunflower heads and set them aside for snacking. Chickens will
            appreciate the diversion of plucking the smaller leftover seeds from dry sunflower heads.

            Seeds collected from buckwheat, pearl millet and oats often contain bits of plant material (chaff) that
            should be winnowed out before storing. Place the seeds to be cleaned in a large bag or pillowcase, and
            crush the seeds with your hands. Remove the chaff by passing the seeds back and forth between two containers
            while standing near a fan outdoors. If using an unheated basement or outbuilding for storage, rotate grains
            into clean containers monthly. This is the best way to spot pest or moisture problems early.</item>

       <item>Summer squash produce male flowers on bare stems, while female flowers — usually preceded by the males
           — show a tiny squash at their base. You can improve yields in small plantings (fewer than five plants) by
           using a small paintbrush to spread pollen from male to female flowers, supplementing insect pollination.Summer
           squash blossoms are edible, and you can harvest fruits from baby-sized up until they toughen with age.
           Harvest at least twice a week, using a sharp knife to cut fruits (leave a small stub of stem attached).
           Promptly wash fruits in cool water and store in the refrigerator. For long-term storage, freeze or dry
           blanched pieces of summer squash.</item>

       <item>Once an ear feels plump and full when you squeeze it, pull back the shuck near the tip and pierce a
           kernel with your fingernail; it’s ready to harvest if the juice is milky.

            Try to harvest sweet corn in the morning, when the ears are cool. Refrigerate them immediately or
           put the corn in a cooler and layer it with ice. Sweet corn can be canned in a pressure canner, but most
           people prefer the speed and convenience of freezing. Blanched corn off the cob takes up much less freezer
           space compared to whole ears.</item>

        <item>Begin checking the root size of fast-maturing varieties 90 days after planting. Sweet potatoes can
            be left in the ground as long as the vines are still growing and nighttime temperatures are above 50
            degrees Fahrenheit. One sign sweet potato plants are done growing is when the leaves and vines turn yellow.
            Starting from the outside of the row, loosen the soil with a digging fork before pulling up the plants by
            their crowns. Some sweet potato varieties develop a cluster of tubers right under the plants, but others
            may set roots several feet from the main clump.

            Before storing sweet potatoes, you will need to cure them, a process that creates a second skin that
            is an incredibly effective seal. To cure sweet potatoes, gently arrange them in a single layer in a warm,
            humid place where temperatures can be held at 80 degrees for seven to 10 days. In warm climates, a well-ventilated
            outbuilding is ideal. In cooler climates, a bathroom or closet with a space heater makes a good curing place
            (put a bucket of water in the room to increase humidity). Another option is to place jugs of hot water in a
            large cooler with your tubers; add new hot water to the jugs daily to keep the space warm and humid.

            After curing, choose damage-free sweet potatoes for long-term storage in a dry place where temperatures
            will stay between 55 and 65 degrees. The flavor and nutritional content of sweet potatoes improves after
            a couple of months of storage. If conditions are ideal, well-cured sweet potatoes will store for up to 10 months.</item>

        <item>Twist off individual outer leaves and compost old leaves that have lost their glossy sheen. Three to
            five leaves can be picked from mature plants at a time, but be sure to leave the growing crown intact.
            Frequent picking helps to stimulate the production of new leaves. Rinse leaves with cool water immediately,
            shake off the excess moisture, and store in plastic bags in the refrigerator for up to four days.

            Excess chard is easy to blanch and freeze, just like spinach, and you can dry perfect leaves and use
            the “flakes” to add color and nutrition to winter soups and stews. Chard stems are sometimes made into
            fermented pickles, or you can pickle the stems and leaves together with a standard vinegar-sugar brine
            before sealing the jars in a waterbath canner.</item>


        <item>Tomato flavor declines at temperatures below 55 degrees, so never keep them in the refrigerator.
            If kept in a warm place, fruits picked when they’re showing stripes or blushes of ripe color will continue
            to ripen. Bumper crops can be preserved by canning, drying or freezing. Tomatoes don’t need to be blanched
            before they are dried or frozen.

            Tomato sauce, salsa, chutney and ketchup can be processed in a water bath canner or a pressure canner,
            depending on acidity levels (always follow recipes when canning). You will need a pressure canner to can
            tomato soup that includes other vegetables.</item>


        <item>For the best flavor, harvest salad turnips when they are less than 2 inches in diameter. Store the greens
            in plastic bags in the refrigerator or freezer. Store salad turnip roots that have had their tops trimmed back
            to 1 inch in the refrigerator for up to several weeks.

            With all-purpose turnips, you can harvest two to three outer leaves per plant every two weeks, and the roots
            will continue to grow. Keep thinning plants and eating the greens, removing those plants that show no signs of
            bulbing. Pull all-purpose turnips when they are more than 2 inches in diameter, and eat or keep the greens.
            Mature turnips with their tops trimmed back to 1 inch will store for three months in plastic bags in the fridge.
            You can also store unwashed, trimmed turnips in damp sand in a root cellar.

            Pull rutabagas when the bulbs are larger than 3 inches in diameter, and immediately trim the tops back
            to half an inch. You can keep your rutabagas refrigerated in plastic bags, or stow them in damp sand in a
            root cellar for longer storage.</item>


        <item>Oats and barley planted in late summer grow into lush, green plants that will regrow if cut back when
            they are 2 feet tall. Use the greens as mulch, or feed them to animals or your compost pile. Allow wheat,
            rye and their relatives to grow until late spring. To utilize them as mulch-producing cover crops, cut the
            plants back to 3 inches when they are knee-high (first cutting), and make a second cutting two weeks later
            before digging out the plants or turning them under.

            With grains you plan to harvest for food, allow the plants to grow uncut. Harvest when the seed heads dry
            to light brown but still show streaks of green. Use a scythe or heavy scissors to cut off the tops, leaving
            about 12 inches of stem attached. Bind big handfuls into bundles (called sheaves) using string or rubber bands
            . Hang your sheaves in a dry place, or arrange them in single layers on a drying table. Depending on weather
            conditions, the grain will be dry enough to thresh in one to two weeks.

            Of the many ways to thresh grain, one of the easiest is to knock the dried tops against the sides of a
            clean barrel or deep bucket. You could also place the grain tops in a clean pillowcase and crunch them with
            your hands. Next, winnow the grain by pouring it back and forth between broad bowls or pans in front of a fan,
            which will blow away the chaff (seed husks and bits of stem).


            Tiny insects often hide in harvested grain, but freezing easily kills them. If you can’t permanently store
            your grain in a freezer, freeze it for a week and then store it in airtight containers in a cool, dry place.</item>


       <item>Fruits are ripe if you cannot easily pierce the rind with your fingernail. Never rush to harvest winter
           squash, though, because immature fruits won’t store well. Unless pests or freezing weather threaten them,
           allow fruits to ripen until the vines begin to die back. Expect to harvest three to five squash per plant.
           Use pruning shears to cut fruits from the vine, leaving 1 inch of stem attached. Clean away dirt with a soft,
           damp cloth, and allow fruits to cure for two weeks in a spot that’s 70 to 80 degrees Fahrenheit. Store cured
           squash in a cool, dry place, such as your basement, a cool closet or even under your bed. Check every two
           weeks for signs of spoilage.</item>







   </string-array>


    <string name="drawer_open">Open navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="drawer_close">Close navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="action_websearch">Web search</string>
    <string name="app_not_available">Sorry, there\'s no web browser available</string>
    <string name="hello_blank_fragment">Hello blank fragment</string>

</resources>
